Previously on Dead City.
With the methane.
we can bring the city back.
Right around the time
that the world turned into shit soup.
The Croat showed up at my door.
Said that I made him feel safe.
He murdered your husband.
Just look after Ginny. will ya?
No!
Our world has been destroyed.
So now. we get to build something new.
Hey. who are you?
You're not supposed to be here.
Do you hear that?
Maybe we should get in there.
No... Sarge told us to hang
these up all around. come on.
Lead the way.
You lead the way.
Always tellin' me what to do.
What the hell are you doing?
You were sleeping.
Armstrong and I got to talking.
She was my responsibility. Mine!
I was... I was tryin' to do you a favor.
You're still healing from the wound.
Where you stabbed me
in the goddamn back?
Never ends with you. does it?
First. you lure me
to this goddamn island.
and then you lie to me.
and then you hand me over
to some psychopath
because you think you're
gonna get your son back.
But you don't get your son back
because he sees the psychopath
as the mama you'll never be.
Don't.
Doesn't end there. though. does it?
No.
Why don't you try murdering me
as the cherry on top
of your shit sundae of shit ideas
and pretend you don't torch
everything you touch
by burying the one person
- on this godforsaken island...
- Listen to me!
I am sorry.
I'm sorry for what I did.
I'm sorry for what you lost.
If I could undo anything
that's been done. I would.
Would you?
This... This is where we are.
And we can either keep rehashing
all this shit
that we can't change.
or we can try to move on.
I have nothin' to move on to
thanks to you.
I'm stayin' put for Hershel.
You got nothin'
and no one to stay put for.
So why don't you go?
I'll help you pack your bags.
Who are you kiddin'?
You're never gonna let me go.
All I am to you. all I ever will be...
is a big old shit pile of the shittiest shit
that I have ever done.
The fact of the matter is.
you need someone as shitty as me
because I am
the only person shitty enough
to make you feel less shitty
about your shit pile of a life.
So do me a favor and go ahead
and keep twistin' that knife.
because we both know
that is the one goddamn thing
that you'll do without screwin' up.
Okay. then you fucking stab me.
Take it. Clean slate. Let's go.
Here.
I don't wanna die. okay?
But I will gladly bleed a little
if it'll make you shut
that gapin' bullshit hole.
So either do it or for the love
of God. shut the fuck up.
It is a one-time offer
with a ten-second expiration date.
so you better get to it... Ten.
- Nine. eight. seven. six...
- You are batshit.
Probably... Five. four...
- Three...
- I'm gonna do it.
- Do it! Two. one...
- Drop your weapons!
She said drop your weapons!
- You got bullets in those guns?
- You wanna find out?
And whatever the hell that is.
What is this. all right?
What do you want?
We were on our way to the cathedral
to steal a methane tank.
Heard you call him Negan.
Rumor has it that's the name
of the Croat's #2.
With your boy here as leverage?
Our plan just got a hell of a lot easier.
My boy?
He just had a knife on me.
I've got nothin' to do with this.
She's lyin'.
She is definitely the Croat's #3.
Listen to me. You...
Both of you. shut up!
Go!
You are makin' a mistake.
The Croat is in the wind.
It's New Babylon who's got control
of those methane tanks now.
So if you want us to get close.
any of us. we get hanged:
you. us. all of us.
Bullshit. Get walking.
- Go.
- Come on. Come on.
- Alley on your right.
- Clear.
Is he your brother?
I see the resemblance.
Yeah. He yours?
No. Definitely no.
Well. you sure as hell fight like it.
Cellar door on your left.
Looks clear.
Mom? Mom?!
- Hershel?
- Mom!
All the dead in this city are going
to be coming this way
after that explosion.
We need to find cover.
We need to find Negan.
Hershel! Hershel. where are you?
Hershel. down here!
Hershel! Can you hear me?!
Mom?
Hershel!
I'm sorry for this.
For what?
That.
God. I so should've stabbed you.
Luis! Luis. you look terrible. my friend.
You're gonna lead us to the tanks.
You're gonna give us one.
and then you're going to die.
The tanks?
What do you think that explosion was?
Tanks are gone.
- What?
- What I created?
Falling into the hands of
those... New Babylon Visigoths?
No. They had to be exploded.
Then you'll make us one.
There won't be time enough for that.
No. Luis! No. no. Come on.
It's not worth it. Luis...
All right. dickhead.
I guess you get the honor.
- Mom!? Are you down here?
- Over here!
Hershel...
- Where's your wrists?
- God.
Luis. it is not safe out here.
We need cover.
There!
What are you doin'?
Renata...
Damn it. leave him!
Shit!
Negan!
I had a feeling our paths would
cross again before the end.
You.
No. no! Stop. stop. stop. stop! Please.
We weren't gonna hurt you.
We were just tryin' to keep a baby alive.
Yvette. the kids wanna
show you the stuffy they made
for the baby.
Aww. It better not make me cry.
Aw. see. Tio Chucho loves it.
As if the world
weren't fucked up enough.
now there's gonna be a little
Chucho runnin' around here?
Can't believe it. dude.
I love you. bro.
I love you. man.
No. no. no. no.
Don't stop on my account.
You have much to celebrate.
My eyes and ears tell me
your family is expanding. yes?
Yes.
Yvette and Chucho are having a baby.
Well. then.
I suppose congratulations are in order.
Flowers from the cemetery.
And the world begins anew?
And yet. Renata...
all this at the very time I have
an issue to address with you.
We have an arrangement. yes?
We protect you.
With respect. the deal was forced on us.
We didn't need it.
So why don't we just end it?
The Burazi protect this island.
The deal ends when you leave it.
Are you leaving?
Our family's been here
a hell of a lot longer
than you guys have.
Well. good for you.
But the arrangement stands.
And the Dama's vision of the future?
Well. it only succeeds if
everyone contributes something
valuable in return.
And as much as I want to
believe you can... I don't.
I was training some of the others
in emergency medicine.
Okay... Doctors!
Doctors are a resource!
Your brother Chucho!
Is he among your trainees?
He is.
Well. Doctor Chucho.
let me take a look at you.
Come. come. come.
So...
Are you a resource. Doctor?
Yes.
Well. then prove it.
No. no. no.
I've given you a patient. Doctor.
Save him.
Don't leave me. tio. Don't leave me!
Stay with me. Stay with me.
You know... I fear he is not
too good at this.
Maybe you are a bad teacher?
Or maybe you are lying to me
about this whole business?
Don't leave me. tio.
Just look at me. tio. No!
I have no choice.
- You just don't make the cut.
- No!
Yvette...
You know.
I was someone's trainee once.
Hopefully better than Chucho.
And one of the many things
my mentor taught me was
that killing the right person
at the right time makes
everyone else fall in line.
So. I wonder...
Did I pick the right person... persons?
Maybe we should try this again?
Who shall be the next patient.
Eenie. meenie. miney...
Renata... Renata...
Do you really believe one
of those slapdash weapons
can save your family?
Everybody back.
I'm willing to die for them.
Are you?
I don't think you would.
You don't know me very well.
This isn't over. For any of you.
Again... Congratulations.
No. Chucho! No. Chucho!
Chucho. please?
They're closed. but there's no lock.
My sister-in-law is having her baby.
We need to go now.
All right. well.
walkers are swarming out there.
There's nothing any of us can
do about that.
Nobody is going anywhere.
He and I are gonna make sure
that this place is safe.
If you would just let us explain.
The baby is coming two months early...
- Nobody...
- If we don't...
kill anybody until we get back.
There's another door up the stairs.
There may be a way out. but it's secure.
Okay.
- How did you...
- I know Ginny's dead.
You know?
I saw you bury her.
And I went looking for you. and...
Just wanted to see if
you were really gonna stay.
You thought that I wouldn't?
I wouldn't blame you if you didn't.
When I got back. the Dama...
She knew what I did.
She started talkin' about how it
wasn't enough for me
to hurt you.
She told me I had to...
She told me I had to kill you.
Just like how I told you to kill him.
I... I think it came from her.
Just being around her.
And I just didn't see it. And I should've.
No. It's what she does. Hershel.
She sees what people
are looking for. what they need.
and she uses it to get what she wants.
It's easier than you would
think to lose yourself.
And you were right to be mad.
Because I wasn't there.
Yeah. after she told me to...
I started thinkin' about
the times you were there.
the scary things you made go away.
You made it so I had a life.
I don't want to spend it being
mad anymore. at you. at anyone.
Me neither.
She's not gonna hurt us anymore.
I won't let her. We won't let her.
Soon as it's safe.
we're gonna get out of here.
go home. and start over.
Hershel. you're gonna move mountains.
You said Yvette is
only 7 months pregnant!
Luis. how can I help you
with your hand on my throat?
Hey. hey!
Were you gonna do anything
to try to stop this?
No. I'm puttin' the little ball
in the little cup.
This sociopath killed our
brother right in front of us
and our uncle.
Okay. maybe...
Maybe I handled things badly.
But I was just trying to make a point.
- As my mentor taught me.
- Mentor?
You said you would help.
They know the baby needs
an incubator to have any chance.
And a tank would make it run.
You need to show us how
to build one now.
There's no need to build.
There's still a tank left.
There is a single prototype
I hid away a long time ago
with plans and detail how to make more.
Where? Where is it?
And I tell you and he kills me? No.
My story does not end
in a musty basement.
No. I'll show you. It's not far from here.
So we go now.
He shows us where the tank is.
Our family's still waiting at
the hospital with the generator.
I told you. you're not gonna
last five minutes out there.
We don't know how long
he'll last in here.
Luis. she's right.
We are no good to anyone dead. okay?
We wait it out here as long
as we can and then we go.
Listen to her. Luis.
Because what I'm offering
has value far beyond the child's life.
It's my legacy.
Imagine your homes with steady power.
your own fields to plow. fauna to hunt.
all surrounded by water.
This island...
It could be your fortress...
Forever.
We just wanna save this baby.
And we will.
When it's safe.
we could use some good fighters
to help us out there.
You can save this baby.
Haven't you learned by now what
happens to people stupid enough
to have hope in this world?
Look. I'm sorry.
You can try whatever you want here.
but that baby doesn't have a chance.
Wow.
You're a real fighter.
You're right.
Where are you goin'?
We're in a bar. right?
I'm gonna go find a drink.
She's still being that way?
And what'd ya say to her?
Well. have you thought about...?
That's classic Titicaca.
Don't you wish that... okay.
I hear you. buddy.
Hey there. amigo.
Quite the fustercluck out there. amiright?
You wanna pull up a stool?
Me and Cockenspiel's
about to start a game
of Fuck. Marry. Kill.
And Titicaca's bein' a wet blanket.
so we could use a third.
And don't worry.
I made these guys nice and safe.
Name's Dillard. Skunky brewski?
Sure.
I thought pullin' teeth would be hard.
but those nails were a real son of a bitch.
He likes you.
Thank you.
Welcome to the bar.
Cheers.
Okay. That should hold.
You could've left the Croat to die.
You didn't.
And because of you.
that baby still has a chance.
San Lazaro.
patron saint of hope and mercy.
It belonged to my dad.
He always told us that we had a choice.
We could choose the fight
or we could choose the light.
So you can just forgive the Croat
- after what he did?
- No.
Never. Making him suffer...
I think about that every single day.
But once the killing starts.
when does it stop?
You know. choosing the light after that...
was the hardest thing I've ever done.
It still is.
But it's a choice
that I wanna keep making.
Me. too.
Just started.
Maybe when we're done here.
Luis can take a look at Negan's back.
I put a knife into it last night.
You. like. just just started.
Okay.
That is dastardly!
Fuck. that is fresh. Cockenspiel.
He's gonna kill Audrey Hep.
marry Venus Williams.
And he says he's gonna bang
Barbara Bush like a screen door
in a twister.
I gotta ask.
Where are you from. man?
What planet do you come from?
Well. I'm actually from Earth.
I'm from here.
Upstairs studio apartment actually.
from way before shit went tits up.
So you have survived here
alone this whole time?
How?
So. over the years.
folks either cut bait or croaked.
But I stayed.
And I stayed above dirt by
turnin' each floor into a link
in a CLVFC.
Closed Loop Vertical Food Chain. okay?
It starts with the deadies who go slip in'
'n slidin' into the basement.
Here we got those maggoes
maggin' on the deadie...
Then you got the froggies
froggin' on the maggoes...
Of course we got the Turks
turkin' on the froggies...
Chain goes all the way up to coyotes.
which are surprisingly delish. by the way.
But I am happy to pump
the brakes on turkeys
if you're feelin' kinda peckish.
Did baloney used to be illegal?
Infection is spreading faster
than I'd hoped.
How can you tell?
Rising body temperature.
redness and swelling growing
outward from the wound.
And see this pus
and milky drainage right there?
Not good.
What can I do to help?
Use that water to clean the wound.
I'll find something to dress it with.
So you think
with those plans you could bring
electricity to the Bricks?
We got someone there who used
to be a plumber tryin'
to figure it out.
My cousin Solmari's an engineer.
You should come back with us.
I mean. it's... It has been
hard there with the crops.
Really hard... But with power...
it could be a fresh start for all of us.
And I need a fresh start.
So what kinda doctor are you?
Emergency medicine.
I'd been training my brother
before the Croat...
Had to brain my uncle after.
But when it came to Chucho.
I just... I couldn't.
You and your people.
you could come with me
and Hershel to The Bricks.
Thanks.
But this godforsaken city has
been our home for generations.
The Croat's right.
The city could still be our home.
Hey. where's the tank?
Tell us where it is.
No. I'm coming with you.
End where I began.
It's not far...
He doesn't have much longer.
We need to go now.
I know it's not safe out there.
but we need your help.
We should help. At least try.
Okay.
And if I had
spilled the beans on that one.
let's just say a whole boatload
of people would've had diarrhea.
- That is not appetizing.
- It's not.
Shit.
Hello. Mason W. Dillard.
Welcome.
The Croat. he doesn't have much time.
We have to go now.
What's the point?
I know that you think that
baby's dead. but that mother.
I know what she's been through.
I know what she's
going through right now.
We need numbers.
Please. We need you.
All right. well. you need numbers.
why don't you ask my pal here. Dillard?
I ain't goin' nowhere.
I need you.
I finally got my son back.
and I need to know that
I'm not gonna lose him again.
I need to know that things can work out.
They can't. Maggie.
Without you. you're probably right.
I'm tired of bein' angry.
Aren't you?
After it's done. Luis can stitch you up
and you can be free of me.
free to do whatever you want.
I just... I need this
one last thing from you.
Please.
God damn it.
I was just gettin' all comfy and settled.
I really should've stabbed you.
You weren't gonna stab me.
I was so gonna stab you a little bit.
- How much further?
- We're close.
- It's just ahead.
- Ahead where?
He needs to tell us where to go!
I got an idea.
Your mother. she sacrificed
everything for you.
What would she say?
Her legacy. your legacy.
is about to disappear forever.
Come on.
Does anybody speak Croatian?
Wait. I think I know where it
is. Keep goin'.
Okay. we're almost there.
I think we're just gonna have
a seat. Maggie.
Okay.
Sorry... I know.
I was so arrogant.
I tried to lead...
someone who only knows...
How to lead.
Hey...
- Solmari. We got it.
- Thank God!
Through those doors.
She's in the O.R. Contractions are close.
- Take this.
- Can I help?
C'mon.
Evie!
Evie. we're here.
Mira. Solmari is setting up
the tank across the hall.
The baby's head is crowning.
Yvette. I'm gonna need you
to start pushing. okay?
I need blankets. water to boil.
and an extension cord for the incubator.
Okay!
Okay.
Come on. That's a good push.
- Another one just like that.
- Okay.
Push .Good. good. good.
C'mon.
Solmari?
When you're done over there.
I need you to come here
and help Hershel.
Why? Where are you going?
Tanks need methane.
Feels like I finally got my brother back.
I'm so proud of him.
I'm sure he's proud of you.
You're just as responsible
as he is for things workin' out.
for what you chose.
I was thinkin' when I go back
to the Bricks
and get things settled down...
maybe your people and my people.
we could be in business.
Maggie. you should bring
your people here.
Hey. everything the Croat said
about this place is true.
It is a fortress.
The only thing that we are
missing is someone who knows how
to keep things safe.
This isn't my home.
Why can't it be? I'm serious. Maggie.
Give me one good reason why
this can't be your fresh start.
I mean. Maggie. you and me together.
Just imagine.
I'll have to think about it.
I have to talk to Hershel.
Of course.
Nothing's more important than family.
Are you really gonna
leave without sayin' goodbye?
Well. you know me.
Never one to overstay my welcome.
Thank you.
For what you did today.
I wasn't sure that I'd convince you.
Well. you did.
How?
I mean. you... You said you needed me.
You know what happened
this morning at Ginny's grave?
There was a lotta shit goin' on.
you know? But...
I wasn't mad at you for tryin'to kill me.
I was mad at you because you didn't.
Why didn't you finish the job. Maggie?
'Cause somewhere inside.
I knew you were capable
of what you did today.
You better be careful.
You're makin' my head
get all kinds of big.
You know. I don't think
I've ever seen you smile.
It suits you.
Well. you need me again...
- You know where I'll be.
- That bar? Really?
Turns out we might not be goin' far.
Thinkin' about staying.
I think Hershel really likes it here.
You really think you can change it here?
Once we find the Dama.
who's left to stop us?
That's it...
God... God.
Shit!
You poor boys.
You're hurt.
Half of Midtown... is gone.
- There's no one left.
- No. There must be others.
You'll rest. you'll heal...
And when you're ready.
you'll help me find them.
And then we begin again.
Every empire starts with the broken.
Yes. our work is just beginning.
This place is the start of something else.
something better.
We could bring in even more people.
Here we go.
The whole. you know.
New York City thing.
it is starting to feel like home.
You and Renata really got
something here. Maggie.
It's your job to protect this place.
This is what we asked for
when we turned on that light.
We've come to make a deal.
It gets in the wrong hands.
it could be dangerous.
If you were in charge.
none of this would be happening.
- What's going on?
- We're taking our home back.
I'm guessing this isn't
your first suicide mission.
Not hardly.
Look out!
Together. we can do something
bigger than we've ever done before.
- You guys rolling?
- Yeah. I mean. I'm rolling.
Yeah.
After this much time we did a season...
- It shocked us.
- That shocked us.
Yeah.
You fucking stabbed me.
It is a one time offer with
a 10-second expiration date.
so you better get to it.
For the first couple
of years I was on the show.
Lauren can hardly look at me.
Her process as an actor. and...
I just didn't have my glasses on.
Maybe didn't have her glasses on.
Sorry. I thought you were
better on your feet.
Good to see you. too.
And then we started this spin off.
Every scene. it was always so heavy.
There was never a lightness
or a humor to it.
We are quite silly people
in a very dark world.
- And now it's...
- And now we...
- we can do it.
- We get to bring that
in front of the camera.
I'm going to flip you around like this.
and you're gonna fucking
Bruce Lee the fuck out of them.
I'm no help.
In this season.
they actually work together.
Heard you call him Negan.
Rumor has it that's the name
of the Croat's number two.
Maggy and Negan are zip tied
together. and there we go.
- Yeah. and you never see us...
- No.
Under other people's control.
They're at it with each other. but this was
a great way of us being joined
in misery against another force.
- Yeah.
- Let's talk about this scene.
We need to find cover.
We need to find Negan.
One of the cellar doors
leading to the street is open.
Beneath the open door. makeshift slide.
A beat later. Maggie.
Negan tumble down the slide.
The walkers immediately on them.
That was a cool sequence
that was sort of
still being worked out
closer to production.
- It got worked out on the day.
- That too.
You were being so nice.
Originally it's a fight
in the streets. remember?
- And it was the dust.
- You had an eye infection.
- I had an eye infection.
- I had a nose.
- a sinus infection.
- Yeah. and we were...
So we couldn't do the super dusty scene.
We were both like.
"We'll die. you know?"
- Yeah.
- My eye is going to fall
out of my head. and she's just gonna die.
Yeah. and my nose
was going into my face.
I know we seem like superheroes. but...
No. just kidding.
I mean. I believe us for
what it's worth working together
that I'm here doing this.
and then Negan comes in.
I'm sorry for this.
For what?
And cut. Good.
It's the first time we've
seen them really fight together
since season... yeah.
It could have been 11.
- We need numbers. please.
- We need you.
I need you.
I think what sets
the whole thing in motion.
of being able to move forward
is. for herself and for her son.
there has to be a life without anger.
There has to be a moving forward.
The possibilities for this new world
and for us are tremendous.
I really should have stabbed you.
You weren't gonna stab me.
I was so gonna stab you a little bit.